<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new charge giuen by the Queenes commandement, to all iustices of peace, and all maiors, shiriffes, and all principall officers of cities, boroughs, and townes corporate, for execution of sundry orders published the last yeere for staie of dearth of graine with certaine additions nowe this present yeere to be well obserued and executed.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Privy Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22691</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9202</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100697</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836527</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836527</idno>
            <idno type="VID">805</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22691)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 805)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 529:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new charge giuen by the Queenes commandement, to all iustices of peace, and all maiors, shiriffes, and all principall officers of cities, boroughs, and townes corporate, for execution of sundry orders published the last yeere for staie of dearth of graine with certaine additions nowe this present yeere to be well obserued and executed.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Privy Council.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Privy Council.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By the deputies of Christopher Barker, printer to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A revision of the orders given in 1594 (STC 9201), in turn a revision of the orders of 1587 (STC 9194).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Food supply --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hotels --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bars (Drinking establishments) --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Taverns (Inns) --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:805:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:805:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A New Charge giuen by the Queenes commandement, to all Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Peace, and all Maiors, Shiriffes, and all principall Officers of Cities, Boroughs, and Townes corporate, for execution of ſundry or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders publiſhed the laſt yeere for ſtaie of dearth of Graine, With certaine additions nowe this preſent yeere to be well obſerued and executed.</p>
            <p>Jmprinted at London by the Deputies of Chriſtopher Barker, Printer to the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie. 1595.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:805:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:805:2"/>
            <head>¶ A new charge for execution of ſundry Orders publiſhed the laſt yere, for ſtay of dearth of Graine; With certaine additions now this preſent yere to be well obſerued and executed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Shiriffe and Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Peace ſhall imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately vpon the receipt of theſe orders,<note place="margin">That the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues into ſundry parts to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute theſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</note> aſſemble them ſelues together with as much ſpeed as they poſſible may: And hauing conferred amongſt themſelues vpon the contents hereof, ſhall firſt for the better execution of the ſame, diuide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into ſundry companies, and take amongeſt them into their charge by ſeuerall diuiſions all the Hundreds, Rapes, or Wapentakes of the ſaid Countie.</p>
            <p>Item, euery companie ſo allotted out,<note place="margin">To appoint ſundry Iuries to enquire of things hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter following.</note> ſhall foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with direct their Precepts vnto the high Conſtables, that the vnder Conſtables, and other the moſt honeſt and ſubſtantiall inhabitantes within the ſame Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, Rape, or Wapentake, to the number of xxxvi. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, moe or fewer, as the quantitie of the Hundred, Rape, or Wapentake ſhall require, to appeare before
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:805:3"/> them at a certaine place, and within as ſhort time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the receipt hereof as they conueniently may, &amp; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the apparance of the ſayde perſons, they ſhall diuide them into ſo many Numbers or companies, as they ſhall thinke meete, giuing inſtruction to the ſayde high Conſtables to returne as fewe of ſuch as bee knowen great Farmours for Corne, or that haue ſtore of graine to ſell, as he can. And ſuch of the perſons ſo warned as ſhall not appeare, but make default being ſommoned, and not hauing any iuſt or reaſonable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe alowable by the Iuſtices, to be puniſhed therefore at the good diſcretions of the Iuſtices, before whom they are to appeare.</p>
            <p>Item, they ſhall firſt declare to the parties appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, the cauſe why they are ſent for, and therewith earneſtly charge them in the feare of God, to apply themſelues to the ſeruice whereunto they ſhal be now called, with al duetifulneſſe and diligence, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any partialitie to any perſon, and then they ſhall giue them the charge following.</p>
            <div type="charge">
               <head>¶ The charge.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The charge to enquire what number of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons be in the houſes of them that haue ſtore of Corne.</note>YOu ſhall diligently and carefully enquire, &amp; make true and due ſearch and triall, what number of perſons of euery houſholder that hath Corne in their Barnes, Stackes or other where, as well Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Peace as others whatſoeuer, within the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> haue in their houſes feeding, lying, and vpriſing, or otherwiſe to be fedde: what number of Acres they haue certainly to be ſowen this yere with any maner of Graine: what bargaines they haue made with any perſon for any kinde of Graine to bee ſolde, by, or to them: to whome and by whom, &amp; vpon what prices they haue made the ſame,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:805:3"/> and what quantitie of any manner of Graine they, or any other haue in their Barnes, Grainers, Loftes, Cellors, or Floores, or otherwiſe to be deliuered vnto them vpon any Bargaine.</p>
               <p>Item, what number of Badgers, Kidders,<note place="margin">For Bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Brog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers of Corne.</note> Brog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers or Carriers of Corne inhabite within the ſayde Pariſh, and whither they doe vſe to carie their Corne which they do buy, and where they do vſually buy the ſame, and what their names bee, and howe long they haue vſed that trade, and by whoſe Licence, and to ſee the ſame Licences of what tenor they are of.</p>
               <p>Item, what number of Mault makers, Bakers,<note place="margin">Mault ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, Bakers, and Brewers.</note> common Brewers or Tiplers dwell within the ſayde Pariſh, and who they are by name, and how long they haue vſed that trade, and howe much they bake or brew in the weeke, and what other trade they haue whereby otherwiſe to liue.</p>
               <p>Item,<note place="margin">Buyers of Corne to ſell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</note> who within the ſayd Pariſh be the buyers of Corne, or doe vſe to buy, or haue bought any Corne or Graine to ſell againe, or haue ſold it againe ſince Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſommer laſt.</p>
               <p>Item,<note place="margin">Buyers of Corne vpon the ground.</note> who within the ſame Pariſh buyeth or haue bought or ſold any Graine vpon the ground, of whom, and to whom hath the ſame bene bought or ſolde, and at what price, and to certifie vnto vs of the Premiſſes, and of euery part thereof, on the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> nowe next comming: And to euery part of theſe Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles you ſhall bring anſwere from point to point.</p>
               <p>And if any ſhall refuſe to declare the trueth, of, or,<note place="margin">Againſt ſuch as ſhal refuſe, to declare the trueth of the matters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirable.</note> concerning the premiſſes, or of any part thereof, to any the Inquirors aforeſayde, requiring the ſame for their better information: the partie ſo required and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ſhalbe conuented before the Iuſtices of the Peace of the ſayde Diuiſion, or any two of them, and ſharply rebuked, or if need be, puniſhed for his contempt. And if the partie ſo called in queſtion, ſhall not declare the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:805:4"/> full trueth thereof to the ſayd Iuſtices, he ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the ſaide Iuſtices to the common Gaile as a perſon bound for his good behauiour, and ſo to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, vntill hee ſhall conforme himſelfe therein, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe at the diſcretions of the ſaid Iuſtices, he ſhall bee bound in a good ſumme of money to make appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance before the Lordes of her Maieſties priuie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to anſwere vnto his contempt in that behalfe,<note place="margin">Parties of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before the Counſaile.</note> for enſample of all ſuch diſobedient perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that haue Corne, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine howe they ſhall ſerue the markets with ſuch por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as they may ſpare.</note>That the ſaide Iuſtices of the Peace hauing recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into their handes the preſentment of the ſaid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirors anſwering to euery poynt of their charge, ſhall call at certayne dayes by them to be aſſigned, ſuch perſons before them of euery Pariſh, as vpon the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment ſo made ſhall appeare to haue Corne to ſpare, and vpon due conſideration of the number of perſons, which euery perſon hath in his houſe, according to their qualities, and of the quantitie of Graine, that the partie hath towarde the finding of the ſame, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe to bee ſpent in his houſe and ſowing of his groundes, allowing to euery Houſeholder for his expenſes in his houſe, for euery perſon thereof ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their qualitie, ſufficient Corne for bread and drinke betweene this and the next Harueſt, and for their ſeede after the rate of the ſowing of that Countrey vpon an Acre. And then they ſhall charge all ſuch as ſhall appeare to haue more of any kinde of Graine, then ſhall ſerue to the vſes aboue menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, aſwell Iuſtices of the Peace as others, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the orders enſuing, viz.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="orders">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:805:4"/>
            <head>¶ The orders to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued are theſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OV ſhall bring,<note place="margin">Orders to bee obſerued by ſuch as ſhal be appointed to ſerue the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets with Corne, for the reliefe of the poore people firſt.</note> or cauſe to bee brought weekely ſo many quarters or buſhels of corne, as Wheate, Rye, Barley, Mault, Peazon, Beanes, or other Graine, or ſo much thereof as ſhall not be directly ſold to the poore Artificers or day Labourers of the Pariſh within which you dwell, by order of the Iuſtices of the Peace of the Diuiſion within which you dwel, or two of them to the Market of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> there to be by you, or at your aſſignement ſold vnto the Queenes ſubiects in open Market by halfe Quarters, two Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhels, one Buſhell or leſſe, as the buyer ſhall require of you, and not in greater quantitie, except it be to a Bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or Carrier of Corne admitted according to the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, or to a common knowen Brewer or Baker,<note place="margin">To whom Corne ſhall be ſold after that the poore are ſerued.</note> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing teſtimonie vnder the hand and ſeale of ſuch two Iuſtices of the Peace at the leaſt of the diuiſion, or of a Maior or other head Officer of the City, Town, or Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough corporate where hee dwelleth, that hee is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Brewer or Baker within the ſame: or to ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſon as ſhall make prouiſion for any Lord Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall or Temporal, Knight, or any other Gentleman that hath no ſufficient prouiſion of Corne, ſo as the ſame perſon haue and ſhewe vnto ſuch perſon as ſhall haue the ouerſight of the Market in that behalfe, teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie vnder the hand and ſeale of the partie for whom hee commeth to the Market to make that prouiſion, declaring that it is for the prouiſion of his houſe, and contayning the quantities and kinde of Graine to bee prouided: And you ſhal not willingly leaue any part of your Corne ſo brought to that Market vnſolde, if mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:805:5"/> bee offered to you for the ſame, by any that are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to buy the ſame, after the vſual price of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket there that day, as long as the Market ſhal laſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No Corne brought to the Market vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out of the towne.</note>Neither ſhall you from the beginning of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, to the full ende thereof, keepe or cauſe to be kept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of your ſaid Corne out of the open ſight of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket: neither ſhall you carry away from the Market Towne any kind of Graine that was brought thither which you haue not there ſold, but ſhall leaue the ſame there in the Market Towne in ſome place knowen, ſo as it may be brought into the open Market the next Market day at the firſt opening of the Market, there to be ſold as afore was limitted. And yet neuertheleſſe, you ſhall bring to the Market ſuch other quantitie of Graine as ſhall bee limitted, and ſo continue at euery Market day the bringing into the open Market, the quantitie of Corne that ſhall be limitted.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">None to buy ſuch kinde of Corne as they ſhall bring to ſell, but by warrant vpon reaſonable cauſe.</note>Alſo you ſhall not buy any maner of ſuch Graine as the ſaid Iuſtices ſhall appoint you to ſell, from this day forwards, but vpon very eſpeciall and neceſſarie cauſe to be allowed by them, vntill ſuch time as all and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch maner Graines as the ſayde Iuſtices at this time ſhall appoint you to ſell, be according to that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment and order by you ſold. And if you ſhall not ſowe ſo much this yeere as hath bene preſented that ye intend to ſowe, or if you now haue, or ſhal haue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or ſhal geſſe hereafter at any time, either by thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of the Mow or Shocks or otherwiſe, that yee haue more ſtore of any manner of Graine, then hath bene preſented: that then ye ſhal forth with vpon ſuch knowledge thereof had, make true relation thereof vnto the ſaid Iuſtices, or vnto two of them, both what portion of your ſeed Corne ſhalbe left vnſowen, or what further quantity you ſhal perceiue you haue, then was at the firſt preſented.</p>
            <p>That ſo ſoone as you perceiue you ſpend not after
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:805:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> the rate of ſo much Corne as is limitted vnto you for the finding of your houſe, ye ſhall make true report vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Iuſtices or two of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how much leſſe ye ſpend.</p>
            <p>Yee ſhall buy no Corne to ſell it againe,<note place="margin">No corne to be bought for to ſell againe.</note> neither ſhall you by any colour directly or indirectly, appoint any your ſeruants, or any other perſon to bee a Badger of your Corne, other then to cary your Corne to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket there to be ſold as your owne, without changing of any propertie.</p>
            <p>Ye ſhal neither buy nor ſel any maner of Corne,<note place="margin">No corne to be bought but in open Market.</note> but in the open Market, vnleſſe the ſame be to ſome poore handicraftes men, or day labourers within the Pariſh wherein you do dwel, that cannot conueniently come to the market Townes, by reaſon of diſtance of place, according to ſuch direction as ſhalbe giuen vnto you in that behalfe by the Iuſtices of the Peace of that Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, within which you doe dwell, or two of them, and to none of theſe aboue one buſhel at a time, and thereof you ſhall keepe or cauſe to bee kept a particular note in writing, to whom you ſhall ſo ſell weekly, and at what prices, ſo as the ſame may appeare to the Iuſtices to be done without fraud or abuſe.</p>
            <p>That the Iuſtices of the Peace within their ſeueral Diuiſions haue ſpeciall regard y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ingroſſers of Corne be carefully ſeene vnto,<note place="margin">Inquirie to be made againſt Engroſſers.</note> and inquiſitions to be made for knowledge of them, &amp; that thereupon they may be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely proceeded with &amp; puniſhed according to the law: and to ſee that none be permitted to buy any Corne to ſell againe, but by ſpeciall licence.</p>
            <p>That they take order with the common Bakers for the baking of Rie, Barley, Peaſe,<note place="margin">Regard to the Bakers for keeping of the ſiſe of bread.</note> and Beanes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the maner of the countrey for the vſe of the poore and that they appoint ſpeciall and fit perſons di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently to ſee the people well dealt withall by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Bakers and Brewers in all Townes and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in their Weights and Aſſizes, hauing alſo regard,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:805:6"/> that the Deputies of the Clerke of the Market do not abuſe themſelues in vnlawfull exactions for Weight and Meaſure, and effectually to inquire for and ſearch out the default therein, and therupon to giue order for puniſhment of the offendor ſeuerely, according to the Law:<note place="margin">Bread faultie in any exceſſe to be ſolde to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of the poore.</note> and where any notable exceſſiue offence ſhall be in the Bakers, to cauſe the bread to bee ſold by them to the poorer ſort vnder the ordinary prices, as in part of puniſhment of the Baker.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No Badger to buy Corne but in open Market, and with ſufficient licence in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note>That no Badgers of corne, Bakers or Brewers buy any Graine, or commune or bargaine for the ſame, but in the time of open Markets, and that but by Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence vnder the handes of the Iuſtices of the Diuiſion where they doe dwell, or three of them, and that they weekely bring their Licence with them to the Market where they do either buy or ſell, or els not to be ſuffered to buy any: And that the Licence containe how much Graine, of what kind, &amp; for what place they are licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to buy and cary, that there bee ſet downe vpon the Licence in writing, the day, place, quantitie, and price at which the Corne is bought, that they take but mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurably for the cariage, baking, and brewing thereof, that they ſhew their bookes weekely to ſuch as the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the Diuiſion wherein they dwel,<note place="margin">The Bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to ſhew weekely their bookes of buying.</note> ſhall appoint for that purpoſe being no Bakers or Badgers of Corn, and that thoſe within euery xiiii. dayes make report to the Iuſtices of the Diuiſion wherein they dwell, how the people are dealt withall by the Badgers, Bakers, and Brewers, and that ſuch as haue ſufficient to liue on, or that are knowen to be of any common euil beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, be not permitted to bee Badgers of Corne, of which ſort commonly the report is that there are too many,<note place="margin">No Iuſtices ſeruant to be a Badger, nor none other, but ſuch as ſhalbe licenſed in open Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> and therefore the ſame would bee remedied and foreſeene: Alſo that no Badgers be permitted but ſuch as the Statute doeth limite, and that no ſeruant of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bee licenced to be a Badger, except ſixe of the Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:805:6"/> at the leaſt ſhall in open Seſſions for ſome neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cauſe allow any ſuch, and that none at all be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Badger, except he be allowed in open ſeſſions, and not to bee, as it is in many places, abuſed for gaine of the Clerke of the Peace, or a Iuſtices Clerke graunted without allowance of the reſt of the Iuſtices in their open Seſſions. And furthermore,<note place="margin">No Badger, Baker, Brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or Puruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to buy Graine, vntill two houres af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the full Market begin.</note> that none bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to buy or prouide Corne in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Market in groſſe, as a Badger or Baker, Brewer, or Purueyour &amp; ſuch like, vpon paine of impriſonment, vntill two houres after the full Market be begunne, that the poore may be firſt ſerued.</p>
            <p>That the ſaid Iuſtices, or two,<note place="margin">Some Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the Market, to ſee the poore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued vpon reaſonable prices.</note> or one of them at the leaſt in euery Diuiſion, ſhall bee perſonally preſent at euery market within their ſeueral Diuiſions, during the whole time of the Market, to ſee the orders to bee taken by the authoritie hereof to be well obſerued, and the poore people prouided of neceſſary Corne, and that with as much fauour in the prices, as by the earneſt perſwaſion of the Iuſtices can be obtained. By this it is not meant to charge any Lorde of Parliament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Iuſtice of Peace, to attende vpon any ſuch ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in any Market, otherwiſe then it ſhall bee with his owne good will: but in all other cauſes tending to the execution of theſe orders, it is hoped that euery perſon of any eſtate, will readily giue aduiſe and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance.</p>
            <p>If there ſhall be any Hundred, Rape,<note place="margin">Where Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in any Hundred, for to appoint ſome rich per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to ſupply the want.</note> or Wapentake within the ſayd Countie, within the which or neere thereunto no ſufficient number of the ſayd Iuſtices of the Peace doe dwell or inhabit, the ſayde Shirife and foure Iuſtices of the Peace of that Countie, ſhall in that caſe appoynt ſome other honeſt Gentleman, or the high Conſtables vnder Conſtables, or ſuch other, graue, honeſt, and ſubſtantiall perſons, not being Corne maſters, dwelling within the ſaide Hundred,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:805:7"/> Rape or Wapentake, as they ſhall by their diſcretions thinke conuenient, to haue the charge, in the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe orders there: whome they ſhal alſo inſtruct how to execute the ſame diligently and vprightly.</p>
            <p>That all good meanes and perſwaſions be vſed by the Iuſtices in their ſeuerall diuiſions,<note place="margin">That mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers exhort the richer ſort to be liberall to helpe the poore with money or victuall need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</note> and by admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions &amp; exhortations in Sermons in the Churches, by the Preachers and Miniſters of the Worde, that the poore may bee ſerued of Corne at conuenient and charitable prices. And to the furtherance thereof, that the richer ſort be earneſtly mooued by Chriſtian cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, to cauſe their Graine to bee ſolde vnder the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prices of the Market to the poorer ſort: A deed of mercy, that will doubtleſſe bee rewarded of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God.</p>
            <p>That there bee no buying or bargeining of any kinde of Corne but in open Market, but onely to poore Artificers and day Labourers as aforeſaide, and that the Iuſtices in their ſeueral Diuiſions, do in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient ſort reſtraine common Maulſters of making Barlie Mault,<note place="margin">To make Mault of otes in countreys where there hath bene vſe thereof.</note> in thoſe countreyes and places where there be Oates ſufficient to make Mault of for the vſe of the people, and to reſtraine as well the brewing of Barley Mault, by or for Alehouſes or common Tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in thoſe Countreis and places, as alſo the exceſſe vſe of any kinde of Mault, by all common Brewers, Maulſters, and common Tiplers, according to the true meaning of this Article: And that the ouera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant conuerting of Barlie into Mault, more then may ſerue for neceſſary vſe be reſtreined.</p>
            <p>And where it is informed that ſundry Maulſters and others haue already engroſſed &amp; taken into their hands great quantities of Barlie, either to be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Mault or otherwiſe to make their profite of it by auauncing the priſes thereof: It is therefore orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the Iuſtices of Peace in their ſeuerall Diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:805:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhall vſe all the care and diligence they may to finde out ſuch Ingroſſers, and to examine them exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly how much of ſuch kinde of Corne they haue already in their handes or haue compounded for, and at what price, and where it is. And thereupon the ſaid Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Peace to take order that ſo much thereof in Barley as ſhall bee thought fit in the diſcretion of the ſame Iuſtices, be brought to ſuch of the next Markets thereunto, as the ſame Iuſtices ſhall aſſigne there to be ſold to the poore people of the Towne and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey adioyning, by the ſacke or Coombe or leſſer quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie, and by no greater quantitie to any one perſon at ſuch reaſonable price, and with ſuch reaſonable gaine as the ſame Iuſtices ſhall thinke fit. And ſuch as ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be found obſtinate to obey this order, to be bound with good ſuerties to anſwere the matter before the Lords of her Maieſties Priuie Counſel at ſome day to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed by the ſame Iuſtices. And the great number of Maulſters to be reduced to fewer perſons, and ſuch as haue other trades to liue by, not to be permitted to vſe Maulting.</p>
            <p>That the Iuſtices vſe all other good meanes poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that are not mentioned in theſe orders,<note place="margin">No waſte of bread Corne ſuperfluouſly, nor any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe thereof but for feeding of people.</note> that the Markets may bee well ſerued, and the poore relieued in their prouiſions during this time of dearth. And that no expenſe of any Graine meete for bread to feede men, be waſted vpon feeding of dogges or other beaſts, neither that any bee ſpent in making ſtuffe called Starche,<note place="margin">None ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to make Starch of any Graine.</note> as of late there hath bene diſcouered great quantity expended in that vaine matter, being in no ſort to be ſuffered to continue, the rather alſo for that there are other things not hurtfull to the food of man, that may ſerue for ſuch purpoſes, if ſuch purpoſes at leaſt were requiſite.</p>
            <p>That the Iuſtices be ſtraightly commaunded to ſee by all good means,<note place="margin">Able poore people to be ſet to worke.</note> that the able people be ſet on worke
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:805:8"/> in houſes of Correction prouided and furniſhed, and there idle vagabounds to be puniſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Stocks of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of workes for poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note>That the Iuſtices doe their beſt to haue conuenient ſtockes of money or wares, to be prouided in euery Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, or other places according to the Statute, for ſetting the poore on worke, and the Iuſtices to vſe all other good and politique meanes within their ſeueral Diuiſions, to continue and maintaine the poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in worke within the pariſh, or at the furtheſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Hundred, or Diuiſion, and namely in clothing Countreyes to charge the Clothiers,<note place="margin">Clothiers to continue their worke-folkes.</note> that haue in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times gayned by that trade, not now in this time of dearth to leaue off his trade, whereby the poore may be ſet on worke.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Souldiers hurt, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent people, to be relieued in their dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling places.</note>That the maimed and hurt Souldiour, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impotent perſons, be carefully ſeene vnto to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued within their ſeuerall Pariſhes, Hundreds or Diuiſions, according to the Lawe therein prouided: and that where the prouiſions formerly made, &amp; aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon the houſholders in euery Pariſh be not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, it may be now for this time of dearth charitably encreaſed. And where any Pariſh is not able to giue ſufficient reliefe to ſuch their poore, that pariſh to haue the ſupply of ſuch other pariſhes neere adioyning, as haue fewer poore, and are better able to giue reliefe. And no vagabonde or ſturdie begger, or any that may otherwiſe get their liuing by their labours, bee ſuffered to wander abroad vnder colour of begging in any Towne, fielde or high way, and that the Iuſtices doe preſently giue order that there be able perſons ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and ſufficiently weaponed, to aſſiſt the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables of euery Towne to attache ſuch vagabondes, both in their Townes, Fieldes and high wayes, and to commit them to priſon without bayle of any ſuch, but as two of the Iuſtices of the Peace within that Diuiſion ſhall order. And if any Towneſhip ſhall not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:805:8"/> obſerue this order, for the attaching &amp; puniſhing of the ſaid vagabondes, then the Iuſtices ſhall ſet due pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment by fine vpon the whole Towneſhip, or vpon ſuch parties in the Towne, as ſhall bee founde in fault.</p>
            <p>Where in ſome partes of the Realme,<note place="margin">That no Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers be ſuffered to be common buyers of Corne, nor to ſell meale, but to attend to the true grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the corne brought, and to vſe meaſurable tolle theſe deare ſeaſons.</note> diuers Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, who ought onely to ſerue for grinding of Corne that ſhall be brought to their milles, haue begun late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a very corrupt trade, to be common byers of Corne, both in markets, and out of markets, and the ſame do grinde into meale, and doe vſe as Badgers, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to ſell the ſame at markets and in other places, ſeeking thereby an inordinate gaine, beſides the miſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of other mens Corne brought thither to be grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, by delay of grinding, or that worſe is, by changing and altering of their good Corne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſe: It is thought very neceſſary, that the Iuſtices of the Peace who are not owners by any title of any Milles, nor maſters or landlords to any Millers, ſhal firſt inhibite al Millers vpon paine both of impriſonment and fine, to vſe any ſuch trade of buying of any graine to be ſolde either in Corne or meale, but to charge them to continue the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly vſe of grinding of all maner of Corne that ſhalbe brought to them, in reaſonable good ſort, and vpon reaſonable Tolle. And for better performance hereof ſome of the Iuſtices not affectionated to the Millers, ſhall ſometime perſonally themſelues reſort to the mills to ouerſee the doings of the ſaid Millers, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell them to doe their dueties. And where none of the Iuſtices can as need ſhalbe, weekely looke thereto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally, they ſhall appoint certaine honeſt perſons weekely to attend thereto, and to enforme themſelues of the poorer ſort, howe they are vſed in this time of dearth, for their grinding and their Toll, and preſent the defaults to the Iuſtices, to bee ſpeedily reformed with all due ſeueritie.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:805:9"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Conferences to be had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of peace in the Shires, and the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall officers of Cities and townes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions of Graine, for the inhabitants in Cities and corporate Townes.</note>Item, where there are within the circuite of any Shire, or thereto adioyning any Cities that are incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated as Townes within them ſelues, or any other Townes incorporat, that haue by good authoritie Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of Peace of their owne inhabitants, for that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſuch Cities and Townes haue their greateſt number of houſholders that are no owners of graine, but haue common Bakers, and Brewers, that muſt of neceſſitie buy and prouide their Corne or Meale at the Markets neere thereto, to ſerue all other the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants and reſiants within the ſaid Cities &amp; Townes: For the prouiſion of all ſuch Cities and Townes, it ſhall be neceſſary that the Iuſtices of the Peace of the Shires next to the ſame Cities and Townes ſhal haue a meeting and conference with the head Officers of the ſayd Cities and Townes, howe and in what good manner the Bakers and Brewers, and other houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders that ſhall alſo haue neede to prouide Corne or Meale for the neceſſarie vſe of the priuate houſholdes, may bee prouided at the Markets neere to the ſame. And after due conference had hereof, there ſhall bee by the Iuſtices of Peace, and the foreſaid head Officers ſome good orders ſet downe, ſuch as both may ſerue for the needefull vſe of the ſame Townes and Cities, and alſo may not by abuſe giue cauſe of raiſing of prices in the Markets and Countries adioyning. And where there ſhall be adioyning to the ſame Cities &amp; Townes, or not farre diſtant, diuers Shires (as in many places ſuch is the ſituation of them) there ſome of the Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of euery Shire ſo adioyning, or not farre diſtant, ſhall vſe ſuch conference and take ſuch orders with the ſaide Officers, as afore is mentioned. And in ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the Iuſtices of euery ſuch Shire ſhall be enformed mutually from the one Shire vnto the other, of the needefull prouiſions to be made from time to time for the ſaid Cities and Townes, ſo as euery Shire may
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:805:9"/> proportionably yeelde reaſonable ſuccour and reliefe out of their Markets to the Purueyors, or to the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, and Brewers as ſhall be requiſite without bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening of the one, more then the other may reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beare. And if neede ſhall require, the aforeſaid prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Officers ſhall not refuſe to acquaint the Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, from whence the prouiſion ſhall bee bought and prouided, howe ſuch prouiſions ſo had and bought in Markets are ſpent, that by colour of ſuch prouiſions no abuſe be committed to encreaſe the prices, and ſo to leaue the poore vnable to be relieued.</p>
            <p>If there bee any ſpeciall part within any Shire,<note place="margin">Order for pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces exempt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d from the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the Iuſtices of peace in the bodies of the Shires.</note> that hath as a libertie by ſpeciall Commiſſions any Iuſtices of the Peace within the ſame, the Shirife of the Shire ſhall ſend vnto the principall owner or Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of ſuch Libertie, notice of theſe orders, and ſhall charge them that the Iuſtices of the Peace within ſuch Libertie doe their dueties for execution of al theſe orders, as farre foorth as ſhall be requiſite, and therein alſo to vſe by conference the aduiſe of ſome other Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices next adioyning.</p>
            <p>That no tranſportation of Corne or Victual be,<note place="margin">Regard to ſtay all tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Graine out of the Realme.</note> but from porte to porte within this Realme, and that but in caſes needfull, as for the prouiſions of London, ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, or ſuch like. And that be done by the view and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſeeing of her Maieſties officers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cuſtome houſe of the porte where the ſame ſhalbe laden, or of the moſt part of them, &amp; of the chiefe magiſtrates of the town in which that port is, &amp; alſo of ſome of the Commiſſioners of the county in which that port is, &amp; for that purpoſe aſſigned. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in ſuch caſe good bonds with ſufficient ſureties be taken to her Maieſties vſe for the deliuerie therof at the port to which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſhalbe aſſigned. And for bringing backe in conuenient time not only a true Certificate of the vnlading thereof at the ſame porte ſo aſſigned from her Maieſties officers of the Cuſtome
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:805:10"/> houſe of that porte to the Cuſtomer of the porte where the ſame was laden: But alſo one other Certificate from the chiefe magiſtrate of the Towne of that porte where the ſame ſhalbe aſſigned to be vnladen: And fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome of the Commiſſioners of the Countie in which that Towne is, for the purpoſe aſſigned vnto the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners and chiefe magiſtrate of that porte where the ſame was laden, of the due and iuſt vnlading thereof at the porte aſſigned. And tranſcripts of thoſe Certificates to bee made &amp; certified into the Eſchequer in the beginning of euery Terme.</p>
            <p>And if the Commiſſioners for that purpoſe aſſigned, ſhall not doe their beſt endeuours to make ſtay of the tranſporting of Corne, as by authoritie of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion they ought to doe, then any other Iuſtice by authority of theſe orders ſhal make ſtay of al ſuch tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation, and in his ſo doing, ſhall be allowed &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. And this is thought meete to be in this ſort di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, for that it may be doubted, that amongeſt ſo many as are appointed in the foreſaid Commiſſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt tranſportation, ſome may be miſtaken, being themſelues either tranſporters, or friendes or fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers to tranſporters, or negligent in the execution of the charge committed to them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Certificate to be made of the Execution of theſe Orders monethly to the Sheriffe, and he to certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the ſame to the priuie Councel with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in euery fourty dayes.</note>That the Iuſtices of the Peace doe once euery mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth certifie their doings and proceedings by force of theſe inſtructions vnto the Sheriffe of the ſayd Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in which certificate they ſhall alſo make certificate of ſuch Iuſtices as ſhal be abſent from any of theſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices, and the true cauſe of their abſence, and ſhall alſo certifie the vſuall prices of all kindes of Graine in their markets for that moneth paſt: Of all which the ſame Sherife ſhall certifie to the Priuie counſell with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any delay, ſo as he doe certifie once in euery fourtie dayes at the furtheſt, and ſo as alſo the default in any Iuſtice that ſhall be abſent without neceſſary cauſe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:805:10"/> may be duely conſidered, and reformed by authoritie of her Maieſties Counſell, as reaſon ſhall require: whereby ſuch perſons as are placed as Iuſtices, may not continue in thoſe roomes wherein they ſhall be founde not diſpoſed to attende ſuch neceſſary and godly ſeruices as this is, but that others of better diſpoſition may ſupply thoſe roomes, if there ſhall be neede of any ſuch number.</p>
            <p>Speciall Inquirie bee made of thoſe that are great hoorders vp of Corne, and bring litle quantitie to the Market, to the ende from ſuch perſons prouiſion may bee made for her Maieſties ſhipping, &amp; other publique ſeruices, as need ſhall require.</p>
            <p>And if any ſhall offend againſt the true meaning of theſe inſtructions, or of any part thereof, or ſhall vſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſiniſter meane to the defrauding thereof, that ſuch be ſeuerely puniſhed according to the Lawes: and for ſuch obſtinate perſons as ſhall not conforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, the Iuſtices ſhall at their diſcretion bind them to appeare before the Queenes Maieſties priuy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell by a day certaine, there to be further dealt with by ſeuere puniſhment, for the better enſample of all others.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="additions">
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Additions to the former Orders.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt to take order that the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Badgers and byers both of Butter &amp; Cheeſe, as alſo of Corne to ſell againe, may in euery Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vpon conference amongſt the Iuſtices bee reduced to a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent number, and thoſe of the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt perſons for that purpoſe, and the reſidue to be remooued.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:805:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>That ſuch of theſe Badgers and buyers as ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, be only permitted to make prouiſion to furniſh the Markets of ſuch Cities &amp; other great townes and places which otherwiſe are not able to be ſufficiently prouided for, of thoſe prouiſions in the countreys neere adioyning, for that they are onely needfull for thoſe places.</p>
            <p>That the Farmer or Maulſter be not permitted to ſell to any ſuch Badgers or buyer, nor to any Baker or Brewer out of a market, nor that any Badgers or buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to ſell againe, be permitted to buy any Corne, But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or Cheeſe but in the Market: Neither any Baker, Brewer, Badger or ſuch buyer as aforeſayd to ſell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, bee permitted to buy in any market but two houres at the leaſt after the full of the market, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by others may be ſerued of their particular prouiſions, And then the Badger, Baker, and buyer to ſell againe, to take away the ſurpluſage of the Market onely.</p>
            <p>To foreſee that no couenous practiſes be vſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Farmer or Maulſter, &amp; the Badger, Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, Brewer, or buyer to ſell againe, whereby the Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer or other ſhould deteine his Corne or Mault to the ende of the Market to the hinderance of the market: But if any ſuch be found then ſuch offender to be duely puniſhed.</p>
            <p>Hyglers and Purueiors for the Citie of London or any other Citie, not to be permitted to buy Corne or other victuall but in open market, &amp; that two houres after the full Market, whereby the poorer ſort may be ſerued of that which they ſhall neede at competent priſes: Neuertheleſſe, for the better furniſhing of your ſayd Cities with neceſſarie prouiſions and in conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent maner, it is ordered that further prouiſions ſhall be from time to time made for them in ſuch ſort as the Lords of her Maieſties Counſell ſhal further direct in that behalfe.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:805:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>It is alſo ordered, that the feeding of ſheepe with Peaſe or Beanes which is vſed in ſome countreyes for foode be ſpecially forbidden, becauſe in time of dearth the ſame may ſerue the poorer ſort to make bread of.</p>
            <p>That there be monethly a view taken what Corne any Farmer or other perſon vſing to ſell Corne, hath both threſſhed, and by eſtimation in the ſtoage, and to be enioyned to ſell none but in open Market, except to poore artificers and day laborers their neighbors, and to yeelde a due accompt to the Iuſtices, of the expenſe of his Corne, and howe much hee doeth ſell weekely in any Market.</p>
            <p>That inquiſition be made in what places Mault is commonly made to be ſold by ſuch as are called Mault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and who they be. And to take order that by buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ingroſſing of Barley to make Mault, they doe not thereby ſtore vp greater quantitie of Mault then they vſually bring into the Markets, thereby to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end of the yeere to increaſe the price thereof exceſſiuely. Of which abuſe the Iuſtices are to take care to reforme the ſame, and to take order alſo that they ſhall buy their Barley in open Market, and not at the Farmers houſes thereby to foreſtall the Markets, and to enhaunce the prices.</p>
            <p>To take ſtrait order with the common Brewers, that they ſerue no Beere or Ale to any Alehouſekeeper, Victualler, or Tipler, but at ſuch rate and price as by the Iuſtices of the Peace ſhalbe ſet downe and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by authoritie of the Statute of 23. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. And yet the ſame to be well ſodden and well brewed of wholſom grain as it ought to be, vpon pain of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> to be impoſed by the Iuſtices.</p>
            <p>To take a view of the number of Alehouſes, Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alling houſes, and Tippling houſes in euery Towne, pariſh, village and Hamiet within their iuriſdictions, And vpon view had, to conſider what number of them
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:805:12"/> is neceſſary and fit for euery Towne, Pariſh, Village and Hamlet to continue. And thereupon to diſcharge the ſuperfluous number and ſuch as are vnmeete to keepe the ſame, and to allowe a conuenient number, and no more then ſhalbe needfull, and thoſe but in pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces neceſſarie, and the ſame to be in the midſt and heart of the ſayd Townes and Villages, and in no ſort to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low any at the ends of the Towne, Village, or Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, nor in out places or places diſtant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reſt of the Town or Village. And hereafter no licence to be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for victualling or tipling but in euery open quarter Seſſions, &amp; that by the conſent of the moſt part of the Iuſtices there preſent, whoſe names with the number of the houſes licenced in euery Towne or Village the Clerke of the Peace ſhall inſert in a booke, or Rolle to be kept for that purpoſe. And that no greater number be hereafter admitted to keepe Tipling houſes in any Towne or Village, but ſuch as ſhall be agreed at this firſt viewe, and order to be taken therein.</p>
            <p>That they which ſhalbe allowed to be Alehouſekee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and Victuallers, ſhall bee of honeſt conuerſation, and of reaſonable value, and to enter Bonds to her Maieſties vſe to performe the orders following, which Bonds ſhall be by the Clerke of the peace preſented to the Iuſtices in their Seſſions to be ſeene, whether the Conditions are broken: And thereupon the <hi>Cuſtos Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulorum,</hi> or his deputie, to certifie the ſame into the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, and ſuch of them as ſhall refuſe to bee bound, not to be permitted to keepe any Alehouſe.</p>
            <p>That no Victuallers, Tiplers, and Alehouſekee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers haue in their houſes, or doe permit to be brought into their houſes, any Cardes, Dice, or Tables, nor to ſuffer any to play in their houſes, yardes, or backſides, at any Cards, Tables, Dice, or other vnlawful games.</p>
            <p>That no Victualler, Tipler, or Alehouſekeeper ſhal dreſſe, or ſuffer to bee dreſſed or eaten, within his houſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:805:12"/> any fleſh vpon any forbidden day, ſauing in caſe of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of ſickeneſſe, according to the Statute in that behalfe prouided.</p>
            <p>That the Alehouſekeepers doe not brewe in their houſes, nor haue any drinke, but ſuch as ſhall be fit for the inferior ſort of people, and that but of ſome ordinary and reaſonable ſize, and the drinke to be vttered at ſuch price and rate as the Iuſtices ſhal aſſeſſe and ſet downe in their Articles, (and not to maintaine exceſſe) wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by an exceeding great quantitie of barley may bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for bread corne, for the inferior ſort of people.</p>
            <p>That they ſuffer none to eate and tiple, or vittaile in their houſes, but ſuch as are wayfairing men, that ſhall take the ſame to refreſh themſelues in their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage or iorney, or ſuch as ſhall be appointed to lodge or take diet in their houſes, but to deliuer out of their houſes that quantitie of drinke which their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors of the poorer ſort ſhall haue neede of, to be drunke in the houſes of thoſe who fetch or ſend for the ſame, and not elſewhere.</p>
            <p>To permit no tippling at all on the Sabboth day, or holy day in time of diuine ſeruice.</p>
            <p>That no Victualler, Tippler, or Alehouſekeeper, ſhall permit and ſuffer any perſon or perſons to lodge in his houſe aboue a day and a night, but ſuch as hee will anſwere for, as the Statutes in that behalfe made doe require.</p>
            <p>To giue ſtrait order and charge, to euery Conſtable, or other inferior Officer to whom it may appertaine, that euery of them ſhall once in euery fifteene dayes, ſearch and enquire of the defaults and diſorders afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, and ſhall informe the Iuſtices of the peace of the ſame defaults and diſorders if any bee, that the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors therein, may thereupon bee proceeded on and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed according to the lawe. And if it ſhall ſeeme to the Iuſtice, that the pettie Conſtable be either a Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aller,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:805:13"/> or one that ſhall fauour the Victuallers in their faults, then ſome other meete perſon to be appoynted to make the ſaid Inquiſition and Certificate.</p>
            <p>No Tipler to buy any goods of any waifaring man, or other that ſhall bring the ſame to their houſes to ſell, but of ſuch as ſhall bee well knowen vnto them to be of honeſt conuerſation, and whom they ſhall bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble alwayes to produce, or haue to be forth comming.</p>
            <p>All theſe with ſuch other neceſſary Articles, as the Iuſtices of the ſeuerall Counties (to whom the eſtate of the Shire is beſt knowne) ſhall thinke neceſſarie in the ſeuerall Counties to be added, the Alehouſekee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and Victuallers ſhall be bound to obſerue.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, whoſoeuer ſhall vſe tipling, or victualling without licence, or ſhall breake the Orders as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid to be preſcribed to them, to bee proceeded withall, and ſeuerely puniſhed according to the Statute and law in that behalfe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:805:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
